Register of the Murray L. Weidenbaum papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Murray L. Weidenbaum papers
1960-1977
77052
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, pamphlets, and clippings, relating to American federal credit programs, business and inflation, government regulation of business, utility regulation, and military-industrial relations.
Weidenbaum, Murray L.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1977.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1927 Born, Bronx, New York
1948 B.A., City College of New York
1949 M.A., Columbia University
1949-1957 Fiscal economist, United States Bureau of the Budget
1958 Ph.D., Princeton University
1958-1962 Corporate economist, Boeing Company
1962-1963 Senior economist, Stanford Research Institute
1964- Faculty member, Washington University in St. Louis
1969 Author, The Modern Public Sector: New Ways of Doing the Government's Business
1969-1971 Assistant secretary of the treasury for economic policy, Department of the Treasury, United States
1974 Author, The Economics of Peacetime Defense
1974-1995 Director, Center for the Study of American Business (later renamed the Weidenbaum Center), Washington University in St. Louis
1975 Author, Government-Mandated Price Increases: A Neglected Aspect of Inflation
1977 Author, Business, Government, and the Public
1979 Author, The Future of Business Regulation: Private Action and Public Demand
1981-1982 Chairman, Council of Economic Advisors
1988 Author, Rendezvous with Reality: The American Economy After Reagan
1992 Author, Small Wars, Big Defense: Paying for the Military After the Cold War
1995-2000 Chairman, Center for the Study of American Business (later renamed the Weidenbaum Center), Washington University in St. Louis
1996 Author, The Bamboo Network: How Expatriate Chinese Entrepreneurs are Creating a New Economic Superpower in Asia, with Samuel Hughes
2001- Honorary chairman, Weidenbaum Center on the Economy
2004 Author, Business and Government in the Global Marketplace
2008 Author, The Competition of Ideas: The World of Washington Think Tanks
2009 Author, The Competition of Ideas: The World of the Washington Think Tanks
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection documents the career of American economist Murry L. Weidenbaum through speeches and writings, pamphlets, and clippings related to American federal credit programs, business and inflation, government regulation of business, utility regulation, and military-industrial relations.
The majority of the collection consists of Murry L. Weidenbaum's speeches and writings on economic topics such as military markets, defense spending, revenue sharing, subsidies, and government regulation. The writings include statements prepared for the United States Senate and House of Representatives.
Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; United States. Dept. of the Treasury.; Defense contracts--United States.; Economists.; Finance, Public--United States.; Taxation--United States.; United States--Economic policy.; United States--Military policy.; United States--Politics and government--1969-1974.
- Biographical file, 1975, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Center for the Study of American Business (Later renamed the the Weidenbaum Center) annual review and informational booklet, 1975, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
- Speeches and writings (Box 1-3)
  - Printed copies
    - Undated (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - 1959 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - 1960-1969 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - 1970-1977 (Box-folder 1: 6-8)
  - "An Analysis of the Humphrey-Hawkins Bill," statement prepared for Senate Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, undated (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - "Controls or Competition?" testimony before Senate Committee on the Judiciary Subcommittee on Antitrust and Monopoly, undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - "Forecasting Government Expenditures,", undated (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - "Galbraith and the Public Purpose,", undated (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - "Is War Necessary for the American Economy,", undated (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - "The Need to Reduce Government Regulation of Business,", undated (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - "A New Approach to National Priorities and Governmental Decision-Making," statement for "Our Third Century" symposium, Senate Committee on Government Operations, undated (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - "The Second Managerial Revolution: Summary,", undated (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - "Analysis of Military Markets with Special Emphasis on Air Weapons,", 1959 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - "The Changing Structure of the Military Market," Conference on Space Age Technology, American Management Association, 1960 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - "Industrial Impact of Disarmament,", 1961 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - "Outlook for the Aerospace Industry," speech, Annual Business Outlook Conference, 1961 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - "Some Economic Aspects of the Aircraft Industry,", 1961 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - "Inventories of Government Suppliers,", 1962 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - "Costs of Alternative Military Strategies,", 1963 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - "Some Economic Perspective on the Current Defense Cutback," speech, Annual Conference of the American Industrial Development Council, 1965 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - "The Military Market: High Seller Concentration and High Profits," statement to the Subcommittee on Antitrust and Monopoly of the Senate Committee on the Judiciary, 1968 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - "Military Spending in the 1970s: An Upward Trend,", 1968 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - "The Federal Budget for 1970: More Deficit Spending?" speech, Planning Executives Institute, 1969 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - "Planning-Programming-Budgeting Systems,", 1969 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - "After the 90 Days,", 1971 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - "The Case for Revenue Sharing,", 1971 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - "Confessions of a Republican Academic,", 1971 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    Scope and Contents note
    Speech upon assuming the Edward Mallinckrodt Distinguished University Professorship at Washington University, St. Louis
  - "Forecasting Defense Spending,", 1971 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - "Revenue Sharing and the Future of the Public Sector," speech, Economic Club of Detroit, 1971 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - "Subsidies in Federal Credit Programs,", 1971 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - "The Changing Outlook for Military Business,", 1972 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - "Decisions on National Priorities," testimony before the Joint Economic Committee, United States Congress, 1972 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - An Economic Analysis of the Military-Industrial Complex, 1972 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - "Economic Policy in an Election Year," speech, Annual Banquet of the National Economists Club, Washington, D.C., 1972 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Excerpts, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - "Foreign Trade Policy: A Move Toward Protection?,", 1972 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - "Government Policy and Business Decision-Making," Conference on Business' Role in Modern Society, UCLA, 1972 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - "Hidden Subsidies in Government Programs," testimony before the Joint Economic Committee, United States Congress, 1972 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - "How to Live with the Property Tax for Education,", 1972 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - "New Initiatives in National Wage and Price Policy,", 1972 (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - "Rules for Success in Dealing with the Press,", 1972 (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - "Tax Reform or Tax Boost?,", 1972 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - Testimony before the Subcommittee on Priorities and Economy in Government, Joint Economic Committee, United States Congress, 1972 (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - "Your New Financial Competitor,", 1972 (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - "Financing a Cleaner Environment,", 1973 (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - "The Fiscal Outlook,", 1973 (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - "Government Expenditures and National Priorities,", 1973 (Box-folder 2: 29)
  - "The Governmental Competition for Investment Funds," speech, Public Utility Executives Conference, 1973 (Box-folder 2: 30)
  - "Impact of Tax Policy on the American Role in International Trade,", 1973 (Box-folder 2: 31)
  - "Legislating Social Responsibility,", 1973 (Box-folder 2: 32)
  - "Myths About Unemployment,", 1973 (Box-folder 2: 33)
  - "The Need to Encourage Innovation,", 1973 (Box-folder 2: 34)
  - "A New Look at Business in 1973," (Box-folder 2: 35)
  - "A New Look at the Economy," speech, Time Business and Advertising Convention, 1973 (Box-folder 2: 36)
  - "The Post-Watergate Republican Party,", 1973 (Box-folder 2: 37)
  - "Reforming the Congress,", 1973 (Box-folder 2: 38)
  - "Trends in Public Finance,", 1973 (Box-folder 2: 39)
  - "What Will Revenue Sharing Accomplish?,", 1973 (Box-folder 2: 40)
  - "Budget Reform: At Last,", 1974 (Box-folder 2: 41)
  - "The Business Outlook for 1975: The Cloudy Crystal Ball,", 1974 (Box-folder 2: 42)
  - "The Case for Economizing on Government Controls,", 1974 (Box-folder 2: 43)
  - "The Economic Outlook: A Scenario for Recovery," annotated typescript, 1974 (Box-folder 2: 44)
  - "Economic Policy for 1974," (Box-folder 2: 45)
  - "The Federal Government and Inflation,", 1974 (Box-folder 2: 46)
  - "Fighting Inflation: No Easy Answers,", 1974 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - "How to Allocate Energy,", 1974 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - "How to Curb Defense Spending,", 1974 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - "President Ford's Economic Summit,", 1974 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - "A Program for Controlling the Budget,", 1974 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - "Public Policy and the Electric Utilities," statement to Senate Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs, 1974 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - "Reducing the Inflationary Impact of the Federal Budget,", 1974 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Tables on fiscal policy, 1974 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - "Time for Change: A Mid-Course Correction in Economic Policy,", 1974 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - "Why Taxes Should Not Be Reduced Now,", 1974 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - "A Barrier to Capital Formation: Government Controls Over Business," speech, National Investor Relations Institute, 1975 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - "Budget of the U.S. Government for the Fiscal Year 1976,", 1975 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - "The Business Outlook and Government Policy," speech, Conference of Bank Correspondents, 1975 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - "The Case Against Gasoline Rationing,", 1975 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - "Catch the Falling Flag,", 1975 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - "Civil Liberties for Business Executives,", 1975 (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - "Economic Policy: Parrots Versus Economists," statement to Senate Committee on Budget, 1975 (Box-folder 3: 17)
  - "How to Improve Productivity in Government Procurement: Rely More on Profits and Less on Regulation,", 1975 (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - "A Kind Word for Monetary Policy," statement to House of Representatives Committee on Banking, Currency, and Housing, 1975 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - Meeting with House of Representatives Committee on Ways and Means, 1975 (Box-folder 3: 20)
  - "A New Approach to Defense Contracts: More Competition and Less Regulation," statement for Subcommittee on Federal Spending Practices, Efficiency, and Open Government of the Senate Committee on Government Operations, 1975 (Box-folder 3: 21)
  - "The New Wave of Government Regulation of Business,", 1975 (Box-folder 3: 22)
  - Report on Time Magazine Board of Economists meeting, 1975 (Box-folder 3: 23)
  - "The Tax Cut: Putting First Things First," statement to Senate Committee on Finance, 1975 (Box-folder 3: 24)
  - "Tax Policy and the Electric Utilities," testimony for the House Committee on Ways and Means, 1975 (Box-folder 3: 25)
  - "The Case Against an Energy Independence Authority," statement to the Senate Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs, 1976 (Box-folder 3: 26)
  - "The Case Against Government Credit Subsidies for Developing a Synthetic Fuels Industry," statement to the Subcommittee on Energy Research, Development, and Demonstration of the House of Representatives Committee on Science and Technology, 1976 (Box-folder 3: 27)
  - "The Contrast Between Government Planning and Business Planning: Market Orientation Versus Centralized Control,", 1976 (Box-folder 3: 28)
  - "The Disadvantages of Government-Guaranteed Electric Utility Bonds,", 1976 (Box-folder 3: 29)
  - "The Future of the Private Enterprise System: A Counterattack," speech, Southwest Foundation for Free Enterprise, 1976 (Box-folder 3: 30)
  - "Government as Promoter and Subsidizer of Advertising," with Linda Rockwood, 1976 (Box-folder 3: 31)
  - "Government Overregulation and its Effects on Industry," speech, First International Petrochemical Conference, 1976 (Box-folder 3: 32)
  - "The Outlook for 1976," (Box-folder 3: 33)
  - "Overregulation and the Business Response," speech, Northwestern University, 1976 (Box-folder 3: 34)
  - "The Post-Election Economic Outlook," speech, Annual Correspondents Conference, 1976 (Box-folder 3: 35)
  - "The Potential for Reducing Inflationary Pressures by Reforming Government Regulation,", 1976 (Box-folder 3: 36)
  - "Reforming Government Regulation: Basic Concepts and Realistic Alternatives,", 1976 (Box-folder 3: 37)
  - Time Board of Economists meetings, 1976 (Box-folder 3: 38)
  - "An Economic Analysis of the Federal Government's Credit Programs,", 1977 (Box-folder 3: 39)
  - "A Fundamental Reform of Government Regulation,", 1977 (Box-folder 3: 40)
  - "The Future of Business-Government Relations,", 1977 (Box-folder 3: 41)
  - "A Growing 'Loophole': Federal Credit Programs,", 1977 (Box-folder 3: 42)
  - "The New Wave of Government Regulation of Business,", 1977 (Box-folder 3: 43)
  - "The Rising Cost of Government Regulation," with Robert DeFina, 1977 (Box-folder 3: 44)
  - "Strategies for Business Survival in a World of Government Intervention,", 1977 (Box-folder 3: 45)